Register of the Irwin Abrams Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Incremental Materials
  - Subject File, 1900-2002 (Box 22-25)
    - Interchange, 1964-1985 (Box-folder 23: 3)
    - Interchange, educational, 1978-1981 (Box-folder 23: 4-5)
      Includes writings by others
    - International educational exchange, study abroad, 1955-1992 (Box-folder 23: 6)
    - Japanese Americans, Fred Yamamoto, 1942-1944, undated (Box-folder 23: 7)
    - Kuhns, Henry Welty, 1941 (Box-folder 23: 8)
    - Menchu, Rigoberta, 1992 Nobel Peace Prize (Box-folder 23: 9)
    - Menchu, Rigoberta, 1992 Nobel Peace Prize (cont'd.) (Box-folder 24: 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1921-2002 (Box-folder 24: 2)
    - Nonviolence, 1992-1996 (Box-folder 24: 3)
    - Peace Corps origins, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 24: 4)
    - Peace Links, 1989-1997 (Box-folder 24: 5-6)
    - Peace movements in Norway, Russia, and Germany, 1900, 1984 (Box-folder 24: 7)
    - Peace museums, 1993-1997 (Box-folder 24: 8-9)
    - Peace organizations, 1984-1994 (Box-folder 25: 1)
    - Quakers, 1987, undated (Box-folder 25: 2)
    - Rothman, Jay, 1989-1991, undated (Box-folder 25: 3)
    - Study abroad, 1958-1978 (Box-folder 25: 4)
    - "Survivial in a Nuclear Age" symposium, 1985 (Box-folder 25: 5)
    - Templin, Ralph, 1984 (Box-folder 25: 6)
    - Travel, 1959-1963, undated (Box-folder 25: 7-8)
    - World War II, 1927-1943 (Box-folder 25: 9)
    - World War II, coming of, 1937-1940 (Box-folder 25: 10-11)
      Clippings binder illustrating propoganda and European view of U.S. Includes cartoons of David Low.
  - Writings by Others, 1976-1998 (Box 25-26)
    Includes typescripts, lectures, drafts, booklets, and dissertations. Arranged alphabetically by last name of author.
    - General, 1976-1994 (Box-folder 26: 1)
    - Blume, Wilber T., "Beyond Persuasion: In Pursuit of Public Diplomacy,", 1976 (Box-folder 26: 2)
    - Kriegar, David, "A Journey of Hope: Hiroshima, Nagasaki, and Okinawa,", 1998 (Box-folder 26: 3)
    - Mayor, Federico, "United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization," lecture draft, 1995 (Box-folder 26: 4)
    - Senn, Peter R.
      - Friedrich Althoff: A German Who Helped to Shape American Universities,", 1992 (Box-folder 26: 5)
        In acknowledgements section, Senn writes, "Irwin Abrams inspired this paper."
      - "Problems of the Determination of the German Influence on American Fiscal Policy and Taxation Systems: With Emphasis on Gustav Schmoller and Adolph Wagner, 1992 (Box-folder 26: 6)
      - "Sombart's Reception in the English-Speaking World,", 1991 (Box-folder 26: 7)
    - Summy, Ralph, "Hiroshima: Symbol of the Past; Hope of the Future,", 1995 (Box-folder 26: 8)
  - Printed Matter, 1911-2001 (Box 27-38)
    Includes pamphlets, newsletters, monographs, and other printed matter related to peace, peace scholarship, and international education. In English, German, Russian, Polish, French, and Italian. Arranged by format.
    - Calendars, 1979-1994 (Box-folder 27: 1)
    - Catalog, Antioch International Program, undated (Box-folder 27: 2)
    - Clippings, 1940-2000 (Box-folder 27: 3)
    - Comic book, König Popiel und Die Mäuse, undated (Box-folder 27: 4)
    - Conference reports and programs, 1960-1988 (Box-folder 27: 5-7)
    - Leaflets, 1937-1994, undated (Box-folder 27: 8)
      Includes leaflets of IPRA Commission on Nonviolence, Richardson Institute for Peace Studies, the Peace Studies Association, and the Carl Duisberg Society
    - Monographs
      - General
        - Undated (Box-folder 28: 1)
        - 1940s (Box-folder 28: 2)
        - 1950s (Box-folder 28: 3)
        - 1960s (Box-folder 28: 4-6)
        - 1960s (cont'd.) (Box-folder 29: 1-2)
        - 1970s (Box-folder 29: 3-5)
        - 1980s (Box-folder 30: 1-3)
        - 1990s (Box-folder 30: 4)
      - Handbooks, 1967-1981 (Box-folder 30: 5)
    - Pamphlets
      - "Asia, Africa, Latin America: Expanding Educational Travel," Council on Student Travel, undated (Box-folder 30: 6)
      - "The College Center of the Finger Lakes, Atelier in Paris, France,", undated (Box-folder 30: 7)
      - "Conscience Compels Them,", undated (Box-folder 30: 8)
      - "The Discovery of the Consumer," Beatrice Webb, undated (Box-folder 30: 9)
      - "Federal Convicts Numbers 1128 and 1129, College to Prison,", undated (Box-folder 30: 10)
      - "A Guide for Friends on Conscientious Objection to War," Ben Richmond, Friends United Meeting, undated (Box-folder 31: 1)
      - "How Can We Better Educate Americans to Work and to Study Abroad?" Gerard J. Mangone, undated (Box-folder 31: 2)
      - "IG-Farben, Auschwitz, Mass Murder: On the Guilt of IG-Farben from the Documents on the Auschwitz Trial," edited by the Working Group of Former Prisoners of the Auschwitz Concentration Camp of the Committee of Anti-Fascist Resistance Fighters in the German Democractic Republic (Box-folder 31: 3)
      - "Our Money: How it Works," Jerry Voorhis, Workers Education Bureau of America, undated (Box-folder 31: 4)
      - "Peace in Action,", undated (Box-folder 31: 5)
      - "A Peace to End Wars?" Betty Muther Jacob, High School Civilian Service, undated (Box-folder 31: 6)
      - "Preparation for Peace," International Peace Academy, undated (Box-folder 31: 7)
      - "Ready for India? Guildlines for Callison Students Going to Bangalore,", undated (Box-folder 31: 8)
      - "Reflections on Non-Alignment: From Belgrade to Harare," Homer Jack, undated (Box-folder 31: 9)
      - "The Relevance of an Impossible Ideal: An Answer to the Views of Reinhold Niebuhr," G. H. C. Macgregor, undated (Box-folder 31: 10)
      - "The Road to War, 1945-1951," John M. Swomley, Jr., undated (Box-folder 31: 11)
      - "What About the Conscientious Objector? A Supplement to the Pacifist Handbook," Joint Committee on the Conscientious Objector, undated (Box-folder 31: 12)
      - "What Are You Going To Do About It? The Case for Constructive Peace," Aldous Huxley, undated (Box-folder 31: 13)
      - "Winning the War on the Spiritual Front: A Study Course on Organizing the Peace," Commission to Study the Organization of Peace, undated (Box-folder 31: 14)
      - "World Court Project: Nuclear Weapons on Trial,", undated (Box-folder 31: 15)
      - "Les documents officiels sure les origines de la gueere,", 1929 (Box-folder 31: 16)
      - "Training for Peace," Richard B. Gregg, 1937 (Box-folder 31: 17)
      - "Selections from War Without Violence," Krishnalal Shridharani, 1939 (Box-folder 31: 18)
      - "Shall We Send Our Youth to War?" Herbert Hoover, 1939 (Box-folder 31: 19)
      - "War Aims," G. D. H. Cole, 1939 (Box-folder 31: 20)
      - "World Unity," Maxwell Garnett, 1939 (Box-folder 31: 21)
      - "For Civilization," C. E. M. Joad, 1940 (Box-folder 31: 22)
      - "Pacifist Handbook," American Friends Service Committee, Brethren Board of Christian Education, Fellowship of Reconcilitaion, et al., 1940 (Box-folder 31: 23)
      - "The Rights of Man," Harold Laski, 1940 (Box-folder 31: 24)
      - "1917 and 1941," Frederick B. Artz (Box-folder 31: 25)
      - "America's Peace Aims: A Committee Report," Catholic Association for International Peace, 1941 (Box-folder 31: 26)
      - "Pacifism and Its Opponents in the Light of Value Theory," Geroge W. Hartmann, 1941 (Box-folder 31: 27)
      - "Why Britain Fights," R. H. Tawney, 1941 (Box-folder 31: 28)
      - "World Organization, 1920-1940,", 1941 (Box-folder 31: 29)
      - "The World Society: A Joint Report," Catholic Association for International Peace, 1941 (Box-folder 31: 30)
      - "America's Pacifist Minority,", 1942 (Box-folder 32: 1)
      - "Pacifism and Invasion," Jessie Wallace Hughan, War Resisters League, 1942 (Box-folder 32: 2)
      - "A Plea for an Immediate Peace by Negotaion," George W. Hartmann, War Resisters League, 1942 (Box-folder 32: 3)
      - "We the Offenders,", circa 1947 (Box-folder 32: 4)
        Includes American Friends Service Committee report
      - "Conscience and the Commonwealth," Milton Mayer, 1944 (Box-folder 32: 5)
      - "Build Peace Through International Work Camps,", circa 1948 (Box-folder 32: 6)
      - "The Role of the State in the Socialist Transformation of the Economy of the U.S.S.R.," K. V. Ostrovityanov, 1951 (Box-folder 32: 7)
      - "The Soviet Workers and Their Unions,", 1952 (Box-folder 32: 8)
      - "Deutschland und die Vereinigten Staaten,", 1956 (Box-folder 32: 9)
      - "American Students Abroad: Goodwill Ambassadors?" Syracuse University, 1958 (Box-folder 32: 10)
      - "New Americans in Old Societies," Gerard J. Mangone, Syracuse University, 1958 (Box-folder 32: 11)
      - "A Review of Negro Segregation in the United States," Independent Service for Information on the Vienna Youth Festival, 1959 (Box-folder 32: 12)
      - "Young Voices in Soviet Literature," Independent Service for Information on the Vienna Youth Festival, 1959 (Box-folder 32: 13)
      - "The College and the University in International Affairs: Summary of a Discussion by the Trustees of the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching,", 1960 (Box-folder 32: 14)
      - "Studium Berolinense,", 1960 (Box-folder 32: 15)
      - "The University and World: A Report to the Chancellor of a Faculty Committee of the University of Kansas,", 1960 (Box-folder 32: 16)
      - "USA,", 1960 (Box-folder 32: 17)
        In Russian
      - "Americans Abroad: Questions You'll Be Asked About Your Country,", 1961 (Box-folder 32: 18)
      - "Musees de l'union sovietique,", 1961 (Box-folder 32: 19)
      - "A Youth Corps for Service Abroad," Maurice L. Albertson, Pauline E. Birky, Andrew E. Rice, 1961 (Box-folder 32: 20)
      - "American Studies Abroad," Walter Johnson, U.S. Advisory Commission on International Educational and Cultural Affairs, 1963 (Box-folder 32: 21)
      - "New Goliards," Institute for American Universities, Aix-en-Provence, France, 1963 (Box-folder 32: 22)
      - "A Premilinary Study of Acquiring Cross-Cultrual Interaction Skills Through Self-Confrontation," Donald B. Haines, Herbert T. Eachus, 1965 (Box-folder 32: 23)
      - "The University's Responsbility in International Educational Exchange: A Report of the Meeting of the Continuation Committee for Educational Exchange,", 1967 (Box-folder 32: 24)
      - "Education for the Revolutionary World of the Future: Imperatives for Action in New York State,", 1969 (Box-folder 32: 25)
      - "Foto Bilten,", 1969 (Box-folder 32: 26)
      - "The Peace Corps: From Enthusiasm to Disciplined Idealism,", 1969 (Box-folder 32: 27)
      - "U.S. Study Programs and West German Educational Institutions," Thomas Huber, Institute of International Education, 1969 (Box-folder 32: 28)
      - "International Dimensions of Education: A Statement of Policy and Proposed Action by the Regents of the University of the State of New York," State Education Deparment, Albany, 1970 (Box-folder 32: 29)
      - "Diplomacy and International Law,", 1972 (Box-folder 32: 30)
      - "A Global Approach to Higher Education," Ladislav Cerych, International Council for Educational Development, 1972 (Box-folder 33: 1)
      - "Global Dimensions in U.S. Education," Maurice Harari, 1972 (Box-folder 33: 2)
      - "Odyssey II: The Ship-Based Educational Concept," World Campus Afloat, Associations of Colleges and Universities, 1972 (Box-folder 33: 3)
      - "The United Nations University," Harold Taylor, 1973 (Box-folder 33: 4)
      - "Goshen College SST,", 1976 (Box-folder 33: 5)
      - "St. Peter in the World: The World in St. Peter," Gustavus Adolphus College, 1977 (Box-folder 33: 6)
      - "International Association for Shipboard Education,", 1980 (Box-folder 33: 7)
      - "Odnowa,", 1980 (Box-folder 33: 8)
      - "Deutsche Auswärtige Kulturpolitik Seit 1871,", 1981 (Box-folder 33: 9)
      - "Dartmouth XIII: A Soviet-American Dialogue," Philip D. Stewart, 1982 (Box-folder 33: 10)
      - "The Promise of World Peace: A Statement by the Universal House of Justice," Baha'i World Centre, 1985 (Box-folder 33: 11)
      - "New Far-Reaching Soviet Proposals to Rid the World of Nuclear Weapons,", circa 1986 (Box-folder 33: 12)
      - "Hope for the Future," Griscom Morgan, 1987 (Box-folder 33: 13)
      - "Seven Steps to Global Change: Gandhi's Message for Today," Guy de Mallac,", 1987 (Box-folder 33: 14)
      - "M.A. in Peace Studies," University of Lancaster, 1988 (Box-folder 33: 15)
      - "Tambovskiĭ filial Moskovskogo gosudarstvfnnogo instituta kul'tury," V. M. Tiunnuk, 1989 (Box-folder 33: 16)
      - "The 1990 Beyond War Award Ceremony," (Box-folder 33: 17)
      - "Studienzentrum Für Friedensforschung,", 1991 (Box-folder 33: 18)
      - "Women at the Well and Other Journeys Through Palestine," Anastasia Goodstein, 1994 (Box-folder 33: 19)
      - "One World, One Heart," Susan Polis Schutz, 2001 (Box-folder 33: 20)
    - Reports, 1971-1980, undated (Box-folder 33: 21)
    - Serial issues
      Includes newsletters, newspapers, journals, and bulletins. Contains scattered serial issues. Single dates indicate that at least one issue from that year is present. Within date ranges, many gaps occur.
      - Breakthrough, Global Education Associates, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 33: 22)
      - Bulletin of International Interchanges, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 34: 1)
      - The Citizen, 1997 (Box-folder 34: 2)
      - COPRED Peace Chronicle, 1984-1993 (Box-folder 34: 3-7)
        Consortium on Peace Research, Education, and Development
      - Disarmament, 1988 (Box-folder 34: 8)
      - Fellowship: The Journal of the Fellowship of Reconciliation, 1950 (Box-folder 35: 1)
      - Friends Committee on National Legislation
        - Indian Report, 1989 (Box-folder 35: 2)
        - Washington Newsletter, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 35: 3)
      - Friends House Moscow, 1999 (Box-folder 35: 4)
      - Halfyearly Bulletin of the Association Montessori Internationale, undated (Box-folder 35: 5)
      - International Network of Peace Museums, 1993-1999 (Box-folder 35: 6)
      - IPB News, 1992-1996 (Box-folder 35: 7)
        International Peace Bureau
      - International Peace Research Newsletter, 1989-1999 (Box-folder 35: 8-10)
      - International Peace Research Newsletter (cont'd.), 1989-1999 (Box-folder 36: 1)
      - International Peace Studies Newsletter, 1982-1989 (Box-folder 36: 2)
      - Journal of Communist Studies, 1992 (Box-folder 36: 3)
      - Leading Edge, 1996 (Box-folder 36: 4)
      - Midwest Pacifist Commentator, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 36: 5)
      - Nonviolence International Frontline, 1995 (Box-folder 36: 6)
      - Nonviolent Sanctions, 1994 (Box-folder 36: 7)
      - Occasional Papers in Intercultural Learning, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 36: 8)
      - Occasional Papers on Undergraduate Study, 1965-1978 (Box-folder 36: 9-10)
      - Peace Aims Pamphlets, 1941, undated (Box-folder 36: 11)
      - Peace, Environment, and Education, 1990-1996 (Box-folder 36: 12)
      - Peace, Environment, and Education (cont'd.), 1990-1996 (Box-folder 37: 1-2)
      - Peace Studies Newsletter, 1982 (Box-folder 37: 3)
      - Peace Team News, 1997, 2000 (Box-folder 37: 4)
      - Phnom Penh Post, 1997 (Box-folder 37: 5)
      - The Red Cross Magazine, 1918 (Box-folder 37: 6)
      - Social Action, 1940 (Box-folder 37: 7)
      - Social Education, 1968 (Box-folder 37: 8)
      - Speak German--Sprich Deutsch!, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 37: 9)
      - Strassburger Wochen-Programm, 1911 (Box-folder 37: 10)
      - The Third Alternative, 1984-1994, 1999 (Box-folder 37: 11)
      - Transcontinental Peace Newsletter, 1988-1999 (Box-folder 37: 12)
        Formerly called Transatlantic Peace Newsletter
      - Transcontinental Peace Newsletter (cont'd.), 1988-1999 (Box-folder 38: 1)
      - [Tübingrr] Chronik, 1914 (Box-folder 38: 2)
      - Unclassified: Magazine of the Association of National Security Alumni, 1994 (Box-folder 38: 3)
      - Wiener Blätter Zur Friedensforschung, 1991 (Box-folder 38: 4)
      - Wittenberg Magazine, 2000 (Box-folder 38: 5)
      - Workcamps Across the World, 1960 (Box-folder 38: 6)
      - World Citizen News, 1994-1997 (Box-folder 38: 7)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 26)
    - "Karl-Marx-Stadt, Pionierhaus,", undated (Box-folder 26: 6)
      Ten commercial photographic prints. Possibly from an American Friends Service Committee mission to Germany in 1963.